Guide to the Jack L. Demmons Collection of Photographs of Bonner, Montana Circa 1890s-1960s
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Jack L. Demmons Collection of Photographs of Bonner, Montana
Circa 1890s-1960s
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 905
Demmons, Jack L., 1930-
1,563 electronic files 122 MB of digital material
Assembled in the mid-1970s by Bonner School Superintendent Jack L. Demmons, this collection of approximately 1,600 photographs depicts life in and around Bonner, Montana, from the late 1800s through the 1960s.
Biographical Note
Jack L. Demmons was the Superintendent of the Bonner School from 1974 to 1985. During his tenure, Jack Demmons started collecting photos documenting the history of Bonner, Montana.
Assembled in the mid-1970's by Bonner School Superintendent Jack L. Demmons, this collection of approximately 1,600 photographs depicts life in and around Bonner, Montana, from the late 1800s through the 1960s. Images and descriptive labels were affixed to photoboards for public display. The photoboards and labels were scanned in sections in 2007 with the goal of providing online access to the images.
This collection is one series of photographs and are listed as they appear on the original photoboards.
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and the University of Montana-Missoula.
The original photoboards were transported from Bonner School to the University of Montana for scanning. The photoboards were returned to Bonner School after scanning was completed. The digital files remained at the University of Montana's Archives and Special Collections.
The digital images were created by, and ownership shared with, the Mansfield Library at the University of Montana in 2007.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Bonner School (Missoula, Mont.)--Photographs
Bonner (Mont.)--Photographs; Bonner (Mont.)--Social life and customs
Education--Montana--Bonner--Photographs; Students--Montana--Bonner--Photographs; Teachers--Montana--Bonner--Photographs
Montana; Missoula Valley; Photographs
School superintendents--Montana--Bonner
- Sheep herded through Milltown by the Riverside meat market, undated; Photo caption reads: Riverside Butcher Shop, sheep going thru Milltown. (Lone man in front; several buildings; tallest building says "...AT-MARKET"). Image from Photoboard #1 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 001_b_d)
- Log jam in the Blackfoot River, undated; Photo caption reads: Log jam in Blackfoot River.(Logs behind boom; middle bridge; looking toward the mouth of river). Image from Photoboard #1 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 001_c_d)
- Herding cattle through Milltown, undated; Photo caption reads: Going through Milltown. (Black cows on street; several buildings). Image from Photoboard #1 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 001_d_d)
- Jack Hodge, Milltown butcher, undated; Photo caption reads: Jack Hodge, Milltown butcher. (Stands in Milltown street). Image from Photoboard #1 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 001_e_d)
- Winter jalopy ride, undated; Photo caption reads: Winter ride. (Jalopy; snow on ground; Mt. Jumbo in background). Image from Photoboard #1 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 001_f_d)
- Cecelia Zaugg, undated; Photo caption reads: Cecelia Zaugg. (Studio photograph). Image from Photoboard #1 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 001_g_d)
- Hazel Beadle and Virginia Mathey stand on a trestle, circa 1920; Photo caption reads: Hazel Beadle, Virginia Mathey on the trestle. (Woman wearing a dress and coat holds hand of a toddler wearing a dress and holding a hat; beside train tracks; log yard in background; unidentified trestle). Image from Photoboard #1 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 001_h_d)
- Rita Lavoie (Thibodeau), the skater, circa 1920; Photo caption reads: Rita Lavoie (Thibodeau) "The Skater." (Teen; black coat and hat; skates on ice under low bridge; catwalks in back; circa 1920?; possibly Riverside Park). Image from Photoboard #1 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 001_i_d)
- Workers on temporary trestle by dam, undated; No photo caption. (Workers on temporary trestle by dam; eleven men sitting or standing on trestle). Image from Photoboard #2 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 002_a_d)
- Two unidentified men stand on log pile, undated; Photo caption reads: Left to right: Oscar Peterson. (Two men; one unidentified; stand on log pile in snow). Image from Photoboard #2 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 002_b_d)
- Logs just north of Bonner, undated; Photo caption reads: Logs just north of Bonner. Old swimming hole was by pier. (Looking down Blackfoot toward mill). Image from Photoboard #2 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 002_d_d)
- Crossing the Blackfoot River in the early days, undated; Photo caption reads: Crossing the Blackfoot River in early days. (Three men stand in back of open horse-drawn wagon; in middle of river). Image from Photoboard #2 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 002_e_d)
- Bill Roberts and Carl Larson stand on stack of lumber, undated; Photo caption reads: Bill Roberts and Carl Larson. (Two men standing on pile of boards). Image from Photoboard #2 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 002_f_d)
- Fish caught by Julius Sowre, undated; Photo caption reads: Fish caught by Julius Sowre. (String of fish on line; hands holding line visible on each side). Image from Photoboard #2 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 002_g_d)
- Chaffey Ranch house, undated; Photo caption reads: Chaffey Ranch. (Closeup of house; truck; snow on ground). Image from Photoboard #2 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 002_h_d)
- Horse-drawn lumber wagon, undated; No photo caption. (Two workhorses attached to wagon; snow on ground; two men sitting on load of boards). Image from Photoboard #2 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 002_i_d)
- Alma Rooney, Jeannette Soucie, Genevieve McClellan, Clifford and Margres LaForge, and Wilfred Doucette, undated; Photo caption reads: Left to right: front row: 1. Alma Rooney, 2. Jeannett Soucie, 3. Genevieve McClellan, 4. Clifford LaForge. Back row: 1. 2. Isabel Jones, 3. Wilfred Doucette, 4. Margres LaForge. (Six individuals stand outdoors; woodpile behind people; buildings and wood fence in background). Image from Photoboard #3 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 003_a_d)
- Aftermath of a plane crash in East Piltzville in the 1920s, circa 1920s; Photo caption reads: Aftermath of a plane crash in East Piltzville near the old Smith home in the 1920s. Image from Photoboard #3 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 003_b_d)
- The Rooney children, undated; Photo caption reads: Front row: 1. Carl Rooney, 2. __, 3. Edith Rooney, 4. __. Back row: 1. Bob Rooney, 2. Bill Rooney, 3. Harry Rooney. (Studio photograph). Image from Photoboard #3 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 003_c_d)
- Carl Rooney stands on railroad tracks, undated; Photo caption reads: Carl Rooney. (Standing on railroad tracks). Image from Photoboard #3 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 003_d_d)
- Five men stand on log barge, undated; Photo caption reads: Left to right: 1. __, 2. Me'Me Bellefleur, 3. Wes Fowler, 4, Roy Dishman, 5. Ben Ray. (Men on log barge or bridge; possibly the Missouri River). Image from Photoboard #3 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 003_e_d)
- Helen, Mrs. Fanny, Arthur, and Edith Rooney, circa 1920s; Photo caption reads: Left to right - 1. Helen Rooney, 2. Mrs. Fanny Rooney, 3. Arthur Rooney; 4. Edith Rooney. Image from Photoboard #3 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 003_f_d)
- Mark Nearman and others standing by pieces from airplane crash, undated; Photo caption reads: Aftermath of a crash landing near the old Smith place in East Piltzville in the 1920s. The tall boy at the right is Mark Nearman. Image from Photoboard #3 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 003_g_d)
- Elaine (Anderson) Nagle and others on stage with Santa Claus, undated; Photo caption reads: Elaine (Anderson) Nagle next to Santa Claus. (Group photo; students on stage; school pageant). Image from Photoboard #3 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 003_h_d)
- Unidentified man leaning against truck, undated; No photo caption. (Man leaning against old truck). Image from Photoboard #3 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 003_i_d)
- Old mill, undated; Photo caption reads: Old mill. (Horses hitched to wagons; men on wagons in front; two smokestacks, may not be Bonner Mill, at least in same place). Image from Photoboard #4 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 004_a_d)
- Old Bonner Mill, undated; Photo caption reads: Old mill. (Bonner Mill; horses, two hitched to lumber wagon with 3 men standing on top; railroad tracks; teepee burner). Image from Photoboard #4 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 004_b_d)
- ACM officials (1955), circa 1955; Photo caption reads: ACM officials, Circa 1955. Top Row L to R: Virgil Campbell, Louis LaPaine, Ronald Dix (Mgrs). Bottom Row L to R: Carl Jacobson, Anton Anderson, Emil Elo, Bill Irwin. (Standing on front step of office wearing winter coats). Image from Photoboard #4 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 004_c_d)
- Old mill (1891-1892), Photo caption reads: Old mill (1891-1892). (Mill dam from downstream; water pouring over top). Image from Photoboard #4 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 004_d_d)
- Bonner bunkhouse and community gardens, undated; Photo caption reads: Bonner Bunkhouse. Community Gardens. (Very smoky, especially in background; bunkhouse some 200 feet long, two stories high; large garden area, southeast corner fenced). Image from Photoboard #4 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 004_e_d)
- Bonner community gardens, undated; Photo caption reads: Community gardens. (Smoky at top; ground level shot across lush gardens to the backside of large bunkhouse). Image from Photoboard #4 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 004_f_d)
- View of Bonner Mill from hotel (1925), circa 1925; Photo caption reads: Bonner taken from hotel, circa 1925. (Gardens beyond picket fence; sawmill and teepee burner beyond that; mountain beyond that). Image from Photoboard #4 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 004_g_d)
- LaForge men (3 generations), undated; Photo caption reads: L to R: John LaForge, George LaForge, Clifford LaForge. (Men of different generations in dress suits, hats, and jackets). Image from Photoboard #4 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 004_h_d)
- Bonner Mill office, undated; Photo caption reads: Bonner Mill office. (Six workers walking in front). Image from Photoboard #4 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 004_i_d)
- ACM ripper men feed the slip, undated; Photo caption reads: Before 1908; ACM ripper men feeding the slip; L to R: Bob Martin, Gendrow, Labbe. (Standing on logs on mill pond). Image from Photoboard #5 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 005_a_d)
- Early day Bonner Mill, undated; Photo caption reads: Early day Bonner Mill; At far left, Ray Moss. Second from left, Ed Moss. Others? (Ray and Ed Moss plus four unidentified men standing near three teams of horses, two of which are attached to log wagons with mill building in the background). Image from Photoboard #5 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 005_b_d)
- Tom Fouche, undated; Photo caption reads: Tom Fouche. (In front of large horse barn). Image from Photoboard #5 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 005_c_d)
- Western Lumber Company dinkey, undated; Photo caption reads: 4 men: Western Lumber Company dinkey. It hauled logs along the streetcar tracks to the landing upriver from the highway bridge, and on the west bank of the Blackfoot River. At left, Paul Cyr. Standing at the right, left to right, Jack Motley, brakeman; __; Battiste Godbout, engineer. (Western Lumber Company dinkey no.1 with four men on board; cut logs in foreground). Image from Photoboard #5 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 005_d_d)
- Western Lumber Company, 1911; Photo caption reads: 1911 Western Lumber Co. (Mill photo; tracks, logs and building). Image from Photoboard #5 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 005_e_d)
- Logging sled, undated; No photo caption: (Four white horses pull logging sled; driver on logs; snow). Image from Photoboard #5 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 005_f_d)
- ACM steam jammer, circa 1920; Photo caption reads: ACM steam jammer; circa 1920. (Woods: heavily logged mountain site; white horses; two unidentified men). Image from Photoboard #5 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 005_g_d)
- Clyde Jammer, undated; Photo caption reads: Clyde "Jammer". (On railroad tracks). Image from Photoboard #5 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 005_h_d)
- Driving a logging sled, undated; Photo caption reads: Driver Tom Fouche. (Stands on sled with a dozen logs; four darker horses in woods in snow). Image from Photoboard #5 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 005_i_d)
- Zeph Space, 1942; Photo caption reads: Bonner office. Zeph Space, 1942. Image from Photoboard #6 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 006_a_d)
- Moving into new ACM office, undated; Photo caption reads: 1942 moving into new ACM office. Back row: Leo Pauly, Grant Higgins, John Sinnott, Leon Newport, ???, Bill Lien, Dwight Hughes. Second row: Helen Flynn, Jack Root, Encia Campbell. First row: Mildred Hagaen behind Charlotte Murphy, W.C. Lubrecht, Jim Good, Ben Rae, George Neff, Guy Trenary, Leo Kelley (In dark suit). Three persons unidentified. (On front steps). Image from Photoboard #6 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 006_b_d)
- ACM Mill, undated; Photo caption reads: ACM Mill. (Unknown; view of mill buildings with cut lumber and rail road tracks in foreground; mountain in background). Image from Photoboard #6 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 006_c_d)
- Petaja men, undated; Photo caption reads: L to R: Emil Petaja, Henry Petaja, Walter Petaja, George Petaja, Bill Petaja, Wayne Petaja. (All standing; old car visible in background). Image from Photoboard #6 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 006_d_d)
- Tom Fouche and horse, undated; Photo caption reads: Tom Fouche. (With big work horse standing in front of a building with white picket fence). Image from Photoboard #6 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 006_e_d)
- Mill men, undated; Photo caption reads: L to R: Baptiste Godbout, John Karkanen, Tom Fouche, John Egan. Image from Photoboard #6 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 006_f_d)
- Mill entrance, undated; Photo caption reads: Entrance to mill. (Summer; looking down street to gate with "Anaconda Copper Mining Co." across top). Image from Photoboard #6 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 006_g_d)
- Gunnar Iverson, undated; Photo caption reads: Gunnar Iverson. (Sitting on lumber wagon; with another man driving a team of two white horses). Image from Photoboard #6 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 006_h_d)
- Bonner Store, undated; Photo caption reads: Front of Bonner store. Office was left of store. Horses and delivery wagon to left. Bob Smith ??. (Seven people in all on porch; two horses pulling wagon). Image from Photoboard #6 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 006_i_d)
- Amme Ouilette and I'Rene Levesque, undated; Photo caption reads: Amme Ouilette, I'Rene Levesque. (Men stand; hands in pockets). Image from Photoboard #7 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 007_a_d)
- General Office, undated; Photo caption reads: James Good, ___, Jack Root, Zeph Space, Toivo Hamma, Guy Trenary, Lee Pauley. (Stand between snow banks and white pillar; below sign that reads "General Office"; mill office crew?). Image from Photoboard #7 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 007_b_d)
- Lieutenant Erling Jacobson, undated; Photo caption reads: Leutenant Erling Jacobson, Bonner Lutheran pastor, on leave as Navy Chaplin, Guadalcanal, Solomon Islands WWII. (Man sitting in army jeep with hat held in hand). Image from Photoboard #7 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 007_c_d)
- U.S.S. St. George, undated; Photo caption reads: Chris Lang's ship U.S.S. St. George - Seaplane Tender WWII. Image from Photoboard #7 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 007_d_d)
- Inside Bonner Store, undated; Photo caption reads: Inside store (Bonner) Left: Ray McMillan. (Two men stand in store; looking like proprietors). Image from Photoboard #7 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 007_e_d)
- Office work, undated; No photo caption. (Men at desks and drafting table in spacious office room). Image from Photoboard #7 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 007_f_d)
- Operating the trimmer, undated; Photo caption reads: John Flink operating the trimmer. (Inside mill; John in chair). Image from Photoboard #7 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 007_g_d)
- Dry kiln and stacker, 1937; Photo caption reads: Dry kiln and stacker In 1937. (Looking across middle of mill grounds). Image from Photoboard #7 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 007_h_d)
- Inside the Margaret Hotel, undated; Photo caption reads: Francis Whittaker, Mamie Bellefleur In Margaret Hotel. (Older men sit cross legged in kitchen chairs; in front of picture windows; original caption read "Francis Smith"; "Smith" crossed out and "Witikar" written above "Francis"). Image from Photoboard #7 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 007_i_d)
- Gathering on front stoop, undated; No photo caption. (Several men and boys in front of tall building with bay windows on second story; wooden kegs in front of line of men; a dog sits on one keg). Image from Photoboard #8 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 008_a_d)
- Family portrait, undated; No photo caption. (Man and wife; hold hand of small girl; standing on steps in front of house; partial view of man in doorway). Image from Photoboard #8 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 008_b_d)
- Emma Zaugg Case, undated; Photo caption reads: Emma Zaugg Case. (Studio photograph). Image from Photoboard #8 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 008_c_d)
- Riverside Electric Station, undated; Photo caption reads: Riverside Electric Station "Waiting for a car" Edna Labbe, Freda Johnson, Edward Beaulieu, Russell Beadle, George Petaja, Paul Blanchard, Emma Alger, Berdie Alger, Palmer Alger, Leonard Nelson, Nels Nelson, Tommy Nelson, Lars Nelson, Ed Swanson. Image from Photoboard #8 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 008_d_d)
- Hunting, undated; Photo caption reads: Jalmer Karkanen, Abe LuRaska, Thelma LuRaska, Eino Karkanen. (Hunting; four men in woods; one shooting a rifle). Image from Photoboard #8 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 008_e_d)
- Group of people in front of store, undated; Photo caption reads: First row: ???, St. Maries, Fred R. Thibodeau, "Willie" William Thibodeau. Back row: Joe Pelletier, ???, Edmund Pelletier, ??, ??, Gust Goyer, ??. 2nd from right -- Frank Beaulieu. (Posing in front of store). Image from Photoboard #8 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 008_f_d)
- On the trestle, undated; Photo caption reads: On the trestle. Hannah Anderson, Hazel Beadle. (Bonner Canyon; railroad). Image from Photoboard #8 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 008_g_d)
- Helen and George Cyr, undated; Photo caption reads: Helen and George Cyr. (Woman wearing man's hat; man with arm around woman; trees in background). Image from Photoboard #8 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 008_h_d)
- Edmund Pelletier, undated; Photo caption reads: Edmund Pelletier. (Smoking pipe while sitting in rocker; legs crossed). Image from Photoboard #8 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 008_i_d)
- Posing beside the Cyr home, undated; Photo caption reads: Front row: Fred Thibodeau, Fred Karkanen, Ada Thibodeau, Bill Thibodeau. Back row: Edmund Pelletier, ?, ?, Gust Goyer. Beside the Cyr Home. Back row: Bill Thibodeau, Bill Beaulieu. Front row: Paul Beaulieu, Edward Beaulieu, Mrs. Vital Cyr (Edith Beaulieu), Vital Cyr. Image from Photoboard #9 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 009_a_d)
- Beside the Cyr home., undated; Photo caption reads: Beside the Cyr home. Left to right: Back row: Bill Thibodeau, Bill Beaulieu. Front Row: Paul Beaulieu, Edward Beaulieu, Mrs. Vital Cyr (Edith Beaulieu), Vital Cyr. (Two men in back row standing; two men, one woman and a child in front row sitting; family portrait taken beside Cyr home). Image from Photoboard #9 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 009_b_d)
- Group photo, undated; No photo caption: (Old photograph of 14 people standing with trees in background). Image from Photoboard #9 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 009_c_d)
- Three Hintz men, undated; Photo caption reads: Ray Hintz, Mr. Hintz, Clifford Hintz. (Two young boys standing on furniture with adult man in between). Image from Photoboard #9 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 009_d_d)
- Children posing next to house, 1910; Photo caption reads: This picture taken in 1910 by the house along the Blackfoot River the fourth up from the (Milltown) bridge. George Petaja was six years old then. Taken by a very amateur Photographer very few cameras in those days. Sime Petaja, George Petaja, Senia Petaja, William Petaja, Henry Petaja. Image from Photoboard #9 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 009_e_d)
- Beadle Butcher Shop, undated; Photo caption reads: Beadle Butcher Shop. Left to right: Pearl Hodge, John Wagner, Fred Beadle. (Two men behind counter; woman sitting on stool in front of counter; scale and cash register on counter; meat in glass case under counter). Image from Photoboard #9 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 009_f_d)
- Chief Martintail, undated; Photo caption reads: Chief Martintail "Sam Resurrection" he sold whitefish in gunnysacks in winter of 1908. Poker Jim also did the same. Every fall the Indians and their horses camped up the Blackfoot to hunt deer and elk. They brought the game out on travois and camped where Weimer's garage used to be. Image from Photoboard #9 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 009_g_d)
- Hamalainen Boarding House, undated; Photo caption reads: Hamalainen Boarding House, Milltown. Image from Photoboard #9 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 009_h_d)
- Pat Cyr's Saloon, undated; Photo caption reads: Pat Cyr's Saloon in Milltown across the track from Oscar Hemgren store. (Woman standing in street [foreground] in front of railroad crossing and saloon; man walking away from saloon). Image from Photoboard #9 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 009_i_d)
- Leo Dufresne, 1944; Photo caption reads: Leo Dufresne. August 1944. ("Assigned to the Battleship U.S.S. North Carolina in the Pacific Theatre of operations"). (Sailor uniform; at home). Image from Photoboard #10 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 010_a_d)
- The Agnes and William Dufresne family, 1898; Photo caption reads: Agnes and William Dufresne and family, 1898. Back row: Leandra, Father, Lucien, George, Ernest, Louise (Girrard), Emil. Front row: William Donat, Armand. Image from Photoboard #10 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 010_b_d)
- Mr. and Mrs. Matt Lehti, 1905; Photo caption reads: Mr. and Mrs. Matt Lehti, 1905. (Caption crossed out and seems to be covered up). Image from Photoboard #10 (Digital image Digital Image, Photo number 010_c_d)